[Music]
Heat. Hey. Hey. Hey.
Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening and good day
everybody and welcome back to the Ask a
Bidget show. I hope everyone's doing
great.
Uh today we're going to discuss history.
I'm going to take questions that you all
have asked in the live uh in in the in
the comments. So I'm going to take a
bunch of those. I've chosen a number of
questions. I'll answer as many of these
as possible and if there is still time I
will take some questions from the live
chat after that. So let's see who is
there on the live chat with us. I can
see Daksh. I can see Nikkesh Dahal
Shrihari Nay Capish Agarwal
Netisen random shots Vladimir Putin
Ojasit Kumar Canel geopolitical dub from
indor Aayush Singh namaste rational
thinker Vikash PJ Pratik Vorasomi Jane
Hensy Penguin Namaskarum Rayan freedom
from outcome from Canada good morning
sir chat DSP I'm random shots Latangi
Suresh Netizen Vikash PJ Vladimir Putin
Archan uh Dutch rational thinker
Nikil Barhavi Nikesh Dahal Rudra Narayan
Geopolitical again Bruce Wayne is here.
Sahil Kala mobile manism.
Hello. Um Richard is here. Nick Hill
ashwani tushar kasana canel langi surv
durya anahita salutations. Aayush Yadav
Shirhari Nayar Aush once again Rahul G
Hershel Patel Suraj Satellite
Sineka Duv Sharma Shiv Brody Aniri
Hershel Patel
and everyone else St. Crocodile
St. crocodile and mites Mitra from
Moscow. Well, hello. Hello. Uh, and
everyone else. All right, people. So
good to have you all. Thank you so much
for being on this live stream. And now,
let's get going with as many questions
as we can take today. All right, so
let's do that. What's the first question
that we have for today? One second. Let
me find the questions. Here we are. Here
we are. Rahul Dunak asks a question that
seems to be a question about science.
But how about we turn that into a
history question? We can always do that,
can't we? So the question is, do black
holes lose mass in the form of Hawking
radiation? Can the mass of can the loss
of mass trigger the black hole to become
a neutron star after its mass becomes
less than 1.4 solar masses? The Chundra
Shakhar limit. So let's talk about the
Chundra Shakhar limit. Who was Chundra?
Why is it called the Chundra Shakhar
limit? Who was who is it named after?
this this physics phenomenon or physics
this law of nature right Chundra Shakhar
so it's named after Subramanyam
Chundrahar Subramany Chandra Shakhar was
the first ever astrophysicist to win a
Nobel Prize in physics not just the
first Indian first ever Indian
astrophysicist but the first
astrophysicist from any country to win a
Nobel prize and it's named after him and
Chandra Shakhar was born in well he was
born in Lahore I think in the 19 what
20s or something or 1910s I don't
remember which exact year it was it was
during the British occupation of India
and he was from a Tamil Brahman family
and uh at the age of 15 he he wrote a
physics paper and by the age of 19 he
was on his way to London on an Indian
government scholarship
uh he was he was on his way to Cambridge
and that's where and and on the journey
to Cambridge on the ship.
The ship voyage took about 18 days. And
on that voyage, he did some calculations
that essentially turned the world of
astrophysics around. And he he
discovered that there is a mass a
maximum mass that a neutron star can
have. After a after a star dies, when a
star is dying, what is left behind is a
neutron star. But only stars of only a
certain mass can become a neutron star.
Beyond that the star implodes into
something else. Sorry not not neutron
star white dwarf. Neutrons were not
known at the time. So what is the
maximum mass of a star such that it can
be become a white dwarf. So our sun the
sun that we have is going to be a white
dwarf someday in maybe 5 billion years
or something. But if it was greater in
mass greater than 1.44 solar masses then
it would not become a white dwarf. would
implode and it would become a a neutron
star which is now known now but what if
its mass is such that it can't even
become a neutron star then it becomes a
black hole so Chandra Shakha's work was
all about what happens to stellar
collapse what's the eventual fate of
stars of dying stars so that's what this
was about and he was a great Indian
astrophysicist but he never worked in
India by the age of 19 he left India
because there was no there were no
opportunities in India and he had a
scholarship he was brilliant so he went
to London and in London. His work
conflicted with the work of Arthur
Edington, the greatest astrophysicist of
that time. Sir Arthur Edington,
right? And Arthur Edington was kind of a
mentor to Chandra Shakhar. So Chandra
Shakhar published his paper which kind
of extended the work of Raf Fowler who
was his PhD guide essentially.
But uh General Shaka's work was in was
in conflict with Edington's work and
Edington was the greatest astrophysicist
of the time and Edington believed that
you know these these uh black holes are
are disgusting things. There should be a
law of nature that prevents nature from
behaving in such manner and this is what
stellar buffoonry and all that. So one
day when Chandra Shikhar presented his
his paper his his research in the Royal
Astronomical Society Edington ambushed
him and he arranged such that his talk
will be right after Chandra Shakhar's
talk and Chandra Shakerhar presented
everything properly with all the
equations all the mathematics all the
calculations and after he was done
Edington started to talk and he
unleashed a brutal verbal assault on
Chandra Shakhar the kind of assault you
don't do in polite society
he turned what Chandra Shakha was doing
stellar buffoonry and he completely
disparaged Chundra Shakhar without
showing any mathematical proof that
Chundra Shakhar was wrong because
Chandra Shakhar was never wrong but he
turned Chundra Shakhar into into
essentially an outcast
and because of that Chundra Shakhar had
to leave England and he had to go to the
United States and he spent the rest of
his life in teaching at the University
of Chicago. His first job in the US was
at Yurik's observatory.
So a great son of India who who could
never be an Indian because there are no
opportunities in India and for for 30
years he stayed out of the topic of
black holes.
He stayed away from black holes. That's
how traumatized he was by Edington's
assault on him.
And eventually slowly came back into the
physics of black holes 20 years after
Edington died. And eventually Chandra
Shakhar wrote the greatest book on black
holes
and on his on his 73rd birthday I think
he got the phone call from Stockholm we
you are awarded the Nobel Prize. So
that's the story of Subramanyam Chandra
Shakhar and uh so yeah and then to
answer Rahul's question does a black
hole lose mass in the form of rocking
radiation yes it does it does but can
the loss of mass trigger the black hole
to become a neutron star never not
possible according to the laws of
physics so that's the answer and anyway
if you want to understand the story of
Chundra Shaker I would recommend you
read my new book called the Chundra
Shakerher limit which is available on
Amazon the links will be in the
description I think the link is right
now not in the description I'll add it
to the descript description. Check it
out. It's a great read and it's it's the
story of a great son of India who was
one of the greatest physicists of all
time. It discovered a fundamental law of
nature. So please check out this this
here book the Chundra Shakhar limit
which has just come out which I've just
released. All right, next question is by
Shub.
What did ancient Indians call our land?
Today we call it Bharat Mata. Also, how
did the term bharat mata emerge during
the freedom struggle?
Yeah, good question. Good question. All
right. So, what did ancient Indians,
what did our ancestors call our land?
So, the land has been called by
different names, different terms. So um
one of the terms that has been used was
jamudep which was applied to the entire
Indian subcontinent the land that's
essentially south of the Himalayas.
All of that is Jamu which extends all
the way to Gandhara and the borders of
Persia and eastwards to the borders of
of the borders of Surabumi essentially
which is Southeast Asia and south all
the way to Lanka. So that essentially
all of it is is surumi uh I'm I'm sorry
what it is Jammu Jamudip that's the
subcontinent or the continent of India.
Another term that was used for India was
Arya which is the land of the Arya
people the noble people that's us all of
us no matter what are the skill whatever
skin color we are all Arya people. Uh
the British and the Europeans have tried
to appropriate the terminology of Arya.
they now you so the the the
common understanding today is that aran
means white people which is a lie means
us not the white people the white people
are an area they are not arians they're
not Arya people we are the Arya people
the Indians and the Persians the
original Persians probably not today's
Persians so that was the the Arya people
and our land was called Arya the
Persians had their own term Aryan Vijay
or something like that. So, Jambudip,
Aryawa and of course Bhat. So, how does
this term bat? Where did it come from?
So, one of the ancient clans in India,
the one of the ancient Rigidic clans was
the Barata people
and they were the well their king was
called Diwodas. I think it was his son
Sudas who was at the receiving end of
this coalition confederation of more
than 10 clans. the battle of the 10
kings and Sudas
came out on top. He defeated the entire
coalition with the help of Lord Indra.
Of course, you have to praise Lord
Indrat. So, Sudas and and his father
Diwas, they were kings of the Barata
clan of our ancestors
and the land is named after them. And
there's also King Barat of course the
the son of Shakuntala and Duchant. King
Dusant and his wife Shakuntala they
produced that union produced this this
child called Bharat and he was the
ancestor of the of the Korovas and the
Pandavas wasn't he? So that's another
Bat. So yeah that's that's the different
names that our land has been called by
our ancestors. Today we call it Bat.
Some people call it Bhat Mata. Well let
me tell you that Bat is a masculine
name. Okay. uh Barat was not the the the
name of uh Duchant and Shakumala's
daughter. It was the name of their son.
It's a masculine name. I don't know how
this term bharat mata came about but
maybe it emerged during the independence
the freedom struggle the struggle
against British occupation uh possibly.
So I have not looked into how the term
emerged bat mata but it's something that
everyone uses today. The prime minister
likes to say that well it's good it's
something that unifies India and it's
it's something that resonates with a lot
of lot of Indians so it's fine even if
it's contradictory bat is a masculine
name and you're terming that as mata
well it means motherland of course right
motherland which is fine which is good
because the land is our motherland arry
jamudip bat or you want to call it bat
mata you can also call it arrya mata or
jamudip mata if you
Nothing wrong with that I would say if
you want to call it bat mata perfectly
fine I think that's the commonly used
term today so yeah that's kind of the
history but the original terms where
jamudep and ariat and bharat the Chinese
called India tanju tanju means the
center of heaven or the he the heavenly
land the the abode of heaven so that's
what the Chinese called uh our land and
various Other other people had different
uh names for the land.
Okay.
Feminist Slayer says, "What was the
significance of the Louisiana purchase
in expanding the United States?" Very
interesting question. Not sure we have
taken this question before. So, let's
take it. Let's first go to the map
because the answer to many of our
questions can be found in the map. So,
I'm going to show you something for
reference and then we'll see something
else. So, right now we go uh please.
Now, we go westwards and we take a look
at the map of the United States. These
United States of America, right? This
one here. As you can see, it's it's
essentially half of a continent,
right? The mercantar projection kind of
shows Canada as a gigantic nation
compared to the US. It's it's similar in
size actually. So the United States, as
you can see, it's it's half of a
continent. Now, let me show you the map
of the United States in 1800. Okay,
let's let's go to Google and let's find
out
map of the United States 1800.
Map of the USA 1800.
Let us see.
Okay, check this out.
I'm going to Okay, I'll I'll expand this
on a different screen so that it'll be
easier to see.
Here we have it. Okay, check this out.
Um, so over here, if you can see, um,
the the portion on the right, the green
and the orange and the yellow, all of
that was the United States. only that to
the west you have something called the
colony of Louisiana which belonged to
France as you can see in the in the
center of the screen the colony of
Louisiana which belonged to France can
you see how large it is it was
essentially almost as large as as the
existing United States and then you had
the vice royalty of New Spain which
belonged to Spain
and then you had so-called unclaimed
territory which was which which on is
shown is empty on the map because
nothing existed there. No humans,
nothing or if humans existed, they did
not they did not classify as humans
possibly according to the the the people
of the United States. So the United
States was was
significantly smaller than the United
States you imagine today, wasn't it?
So you had Connecticut, you had
Kentucky, Tennessee, Georgia, South
Carolina, North Carolina, Virginia,
which was the original United States.
Virginia was um the place where uh
Jamestown was founded. The the you the
Americans want to forget about
Jamestown. It's it's an inconvenient
story. And then you have Pennsylvania,
New York, Massachusetts, Rhode Island,
Connecticut, all that. And you had the
western Connecticut western reserve and
you have the Northwest Territory, all
that. So that's all the United States
was. and Louisiana. As you can see, this
large large piece of territory that
extends all the way from Canada to the
Gulf of Mexico, Mexico, Gulf of Mexico,
this gigantic territory belonged to
France. So that's the that's the
background. Okay, that's what you have
to understand before we have this
discussion. Now let's have the
discussion. So the United States was was
this small piece of territory
comparatively uh to today's map. small
piece of territory to the west. You had
this huge piece of territory as almost
as large as the existing US which
belonged to France. Uh and the Louisiana
purchase happened in 1803
at at which time France was ruled by
Shri Napoleon Bonapart Napoleon
and the foreign minister was Mishu
Talleon.
Now the Americans they were interested
in not in the entire territory of
Louisiana but they were interested in
one city. Let me show you once again by
going to the map which city it was
here is map. Yes. So the United States
which was only confined to the west the
eastern part of the map it was
interested in a city called Noel Oron
New Orleans. It's the city where the
Mississippi River drains into the Gulf
of Mexico.
And the Mississippi River starts all the
way up north, by the way. All the way up
north. Gig. It's the largest river
system in the world. So, New Orleans was
an extremely important port. And the
United States wanted to purchase this
port from the French. This fort belonged
to France. It was a French city. Even
today if you go to New Orleans, there's
a French quarter which is the more
cultural side of the city and so on.
That's a that's a digression. So New
Orleans is something that the Americans
coveted. They wanted this port and they
sent uh so you have Thomas Jefferson who
was the president of the US at this
time. Okay. and uh he sent uh a couple
of negotiators, a team of negotiators, a
team of diplomats to Paris, to France,
to Paris to uh negotiate with the French
government for the purchase of New
Orleans, this one city, this one port.
And the Americans were willing to pay
$10 million for this one city. We'll pay
you $10 million. you give you you
transfer the city to us. That was the
objective of the mission of this
diplomatic mission to acquire New
Orleans. The maximum price they were
willing to give as instructed by the
president was $10 million.
Now, Louisiana, this huge territory that
belonged to France, did France actually
control it? Well, not really. France did
not did not have any control over much
of the territory. Only some parts of the
territory were controlled by France. But
on paper, it owned the territory. Much
of the territory was was was well
inhabited. All of it was inhabited by
the native Americans and they were the
true owners of the land. But on paper,
France owned it, but France controlled
just a little portion of it. So the
Americans just wanted New Orleans. They
and the Napoleonic wars and all that is
happening in Europe. So the American
diplomats reach France and they are
willing to negotiate hard. Maximum we
will give you is $10 million. Give us
New Orleans. They go to Paris and Mu
Talon the French foreign minister tells
them you know what we would like to
offer uh we would like to offer uh
Louisiana for $15 million. 15. And the
Americans are shocked. They're stunned.
There's no telephone. There's no
telecommunications. There's no email.
There's no WhatsApp. There's nothing.
Washington and Paris, they're separated
by the Atlantic Ocean. Takes God knows
how much time to travel. There's no
time. And the Americans were worried
that if you don't take the offer right
now, Napoleon may take the offer off the
table and we may lose New Orleans. So
instead of paying $10 million for one
city, the negotiators without consulting
the president of the US, they agreed to
pay $15 million for the entire territory
of Louisiana
and the papers were signed and it
happened. And Thomas Jefferson was fine
with that. So the negotiators, his
diplomats, they correctly assess that
the president, even though he has given
us a hard limit of $10 million for one
city, he'll be okay to purchase the
whole of Louisiana for $15 million.
which is shocking which is like what 8
12 like $15 per square kilometer or
something per square mile less than that
it's a shocking it's a throwaway price
so that's what happened and that
instantly doubled the the territory of
the US in size and the Americans finally
felt that we are a first rate world
power now or we have the potential to be
a first rate world power we're not some
little outpost on the Atlantic bank of
this continent We now own half the
continent and we're going to get rid of
the goddamn natives, the savage natives,
the savages. The goddamn savages. We
shall exterminate them and we shall turn
this into the land of the whatever it
is,
whatever it is, right? So that's that's
what happened. So it was significant. It
was hugely significant. It doubled the
size of the United States. So we we took
a look at the map of the US in 1800.
Right? Let's once again revisit this.
The map of the United States 1800. Now
let's say 1805. See what happens. Boom.
Double.
You see that? Double the size. Look.
Back and forth. Back forth. Back forth.
It doubled the territory of the United
States. It was massively important for
the US. So very significant. Louisiana
purchase
Nirvana Shanks says what was the treaty
of Westfallia how did it change the way
countries dealt with each other and
what's the principle of sovereignty
then thank you for your attention to the
question okay so the treaty of west
falia it was a treaty that was signed in
the 1600 1647 1648
around 1650 okay and this treaty marked
the the end of a significant period of
warfare in Europe. The 30 years war in
the ro in the Holy Roman Empire, the 80
years war between Spain and uh the Dutch
and that sort of thing. All kinds of
warfare was going on forever in the in
in Europe. Europe is full of these
tribal tribalistic little kingdoms and
all that. Some are big, some are small.
If you look at Germany though, Germany
of the time, my goodness, you will have
a heart attack or Yeah. That sort of
thing. So Europe was was marred by
tribal warfare. Yeah. are these kings
and principalities and empires. A little
thing is called an empire if it's in
Europe. That sort of thing. So you had
the 30 years war. You had the war
between Spain and and the Dutch which
which went on for 80 years and all that.
And finally they said that okay let's
let's agree to a set of principles and
we're going to call it the treaty of
Westfallia. So the treaty of Westfallia
was not a single treaty that you sit
down and sign on one paper. It was a
series of agreements or series of
treaties that ended this this entire
period of decades decades of of warfare.
So you had political conflict, you had
uh religious conflict, all kinds of
conflicts layered together we woven
together which was just going on
throughout Europe. So finally uh this
this series of treaties was agreed upon
and it established a set of principles
in Europe which and these principles
were then applied to the rest of the
world because European values are are
universal values right that sort of
thing. So uh the first principle is that
we'll talk about sovereignty. Yeah, we
will talk about sovereignty but the
first principle in Europe which was
established as per the treaty of
Westfallia was that each state each
kingdom so to say or each state let's
say each political state could
independently determine its own official
religion. Now what are we talking about
only one religion right? Christianity.
No, but within Christianity, you had
schisms, you had factions. You had the
Protestants, you had the Calvinists, you
had the Hugenauts, you had the
Lutherans, you had God knows what else,
right? So each state could determine
what will be its official religion with
within Christianity. You go beyond
Christianity, we're going to kill you
all. But if you as long as you stay
within Christianity and what form of
Christianity you want to adopt. All
right, sir. So that is what they call
religious tolerance.
Okay? So we're going to treat Catholics
and Protestants alike. You decide what
your religion will be. I'll decide what
my religion will be. You can be a
Catholic guy. You I'll be I'll be I'll
be Protestant or whatever vice versa,
whatever. And we will call this
tolerance. We shall not tolerate
anything except for Christianity. But
we'll call this tolerance. Okay? So
that's the first thing that each state
could determine its own official
religion and that's called religious
tolerance. Second, importantly, each
state is legally equal. So you may be a
thousand square kilmters, I may be
10,000 square km, that guy may be 100
square km, but as long as you are a
state,
we are all equal, legally equal.
So it's like a nation with a population
of 1 million having the same exact vote
is a nation with a population of 100
million. That sort of thing, right? All
states are equal. In India all states
are equal whether it is a state with 3
million population or or 300 thou 300
million population up is equal to money
manipur right in the in the in the
parliament that sort of thing or or in
in in Indian federalism you get the same
amount of of weight legal weight legal
so you have legal equality so that sort
of thing that principle was a was it
became a thing because of the treaty of
west failure the legal equality of state
I don't care what your size is I don't
care what your power is we're going to
be legally equal. And then there was the
principle of non-inference in internal
affairs. So you do what you want in your
in your country. I I'll I'll look into
it. I may look at it. I may I may see
what's happening, but I will not
interfere and I'll do what I want in my
country. You stay out of it. All right.
Non-inference.
It became a bench. I mean it became a
a principle of international relations.
And then they they normalized diplomacy
and and treaties to resolve conflicts
that became more prominent. So that
essentially laid the groundwork for uh
the international system that we have
today. So we don't go to war. We do
diplomatic negotiations. We arm twist
each other diplomatically. We see who
has more leverage. We do we issue
threats behind closed doors. But we
don't actually go to war. We use e
economic means. We use other means. We
don't go to war. So essentially
international organizations came as a
came out uh emerged as a consequence of
this because if each state has equal
equal legal weight because there is
legal equality then coalitions become
important. So I have 10 members in my
coalition. How many you have? Oh you
only have four. Ah we outnumber you. We
are legally uh a bigger power compared
to you. That sort of thing right? And
one more thing is the end of uh
religious authority.
So the pope was very influential. The
Vatican was super influential, right?
And uh that was ended. So the
interference of of the Vatican in the
internal affairs of of various nations
of various kingdoms that was ended and
there was this gradual as a consequence
a gradual shift towards what they call
secular governance. secularism, the the
the the distinction between the
separation of church and state that came
out of the treaty of West Valia and the
concept of balance of power also came
out of this because now that the the the
the church is no longer interfering and
each uh state has legal equality.
So wherever you have coalitions, we will
see how many states are in which
coalition and how many we have on which
side and that that creates a balance of
power, right? that sort of thing. So all
of this introduced the various key
principles that underpin today's u
international system or or supposedly
underpin today's international system.
State sovereignty that each state
determines its the way it's going to be
run its laws its p its policies its
practices and it this so each state
determines what happens in the state and
it's going to be free from external
interference external influence
non-intervention. You stay out of my
affairs I stay out of your affairs.
legal equality. All states have the same
u uh equal rights in international uh in
the international realm in international
relations and religious pluris pluralism
as long as it is Christianity that sort
of thing. So that is the treaty of
Westfallia and that has that essentially
under underpins the international order
today. the Atlantic Charter, which is
the US-based the US uh the American um
application of this the the the supposed
universality of Western uh western
principles, western whatever it is. Uh
that's the that's the that started with
the Atlantic Charter. It's kind of an
extension of this you could say and it
it uh gave America the pretext of the
the the illusion of of moral superiority
over the world the US and England as
well Britain. So the English speaking
world our they said that our values will
now be the universal values which have
to be you know applied everywhere and
every nation must uphold these values.
That's sort of nonsense. So anyway
that's the treaty of Westfallia. It did
change the way countries deal with with
each other once it was applied to the
entire world.
Math and
okay I can't pronounce the name but
let's take the question. How did dynasty
after dynasty of Turic origin like the
Seljuks, the mash, the Timurids, the
Safavidits, the Ashar, the Kajars etc.
How did they all become Persianized over
time in Iran? but did not become
indicized in India like the Turks of the
Delhi Sultame Sultanat and the Gurani
muggals. Huh? Why is that? So
interesting question. Interesting
question. Cause and effect. Let's look
at cause and effect. I mean they should
teach these things in history classes.
I'm not sure if they do. So the Turks,
we we should actually take the question
of how do how do the Turks become
Muslim? But we'll take that question
after this question. I've also selected
that question. So now how did so we know
that after a certain point in time after
a certain period of history in history
the Turks were all Muslims right all
Turks were Muslims and
the Turks
they served in various u some Turks
acted as as as mercenaries in various
armies whether it is the Abbasid army uh
of the Abbasid Khalif
or various Persian armies or whatever
and the Persians
were the first non-Arabic people
essentially the first major non-Arabic
civilization to become essentially
almost entirely Islamized
right so the Persians were Muslims by
the time the Turks had become Muslim the
Persians were already Muslim
and the Persian in so the Persians were
part of the Islamic world. Correct. Now
in the Islamic world, the Persian
culture, their literature, their
architecture,
their language, all of this was held in
high regard in high esteem.
It was considered to be superior
superior culture superior manifest
manifestation manifestation of Islamic
culture perhaps even superior to the
Arabic uh perhaps perhaps superior to
the Arabic culture maybe some people
would regard it as that
um so that's why
so because Persia was regarded as kind
of the epitome of Islamic culture that's
why everyone wanted to copy th those
that culture obviously right So the
barrier
it doesn't exist that it's it's a
non-Islamic culture. So it's okay to
adopt that because they're also Muslims
and they they they practice this culture
which is regarded very highly in the
entire Islamic world. Let's let's copy
that. Let's become like them. Let's
start using that sort of uh language.
Let's perhaps use Persian as the court
language. Yes. all the and we can hire
some Persian bureaucrats and have them
create keep records for us because
Persian is clearly a better language for
keeping for record keeping and
bookkeeping than the Turk language that
that sort of thing. So that's why Turks
became Persianized and obviously Turks
they later ruled Persia as we know that
that Bardarian Nadesha was not Persian
it was Turkic anyhow. So that's how the
Turks gradually became Persianized
because of the great uh uh prominence
that that Persian culture had in the
Islamic world. Now the Turks also they
they ruled Persia. They conquered and
ruled Persia. They also conquered and
ruled India eventually parts of India at
least didn't they?
And the Turks never became Indianized. I
mean the the Muggal dynasty some of
those those kings they married Indian
ladies but there so by the time you have
someone like who uh for example Akbar
married various Indian ladies Akbar's
mother was not Indian. His mother was
Turk or whatever she was but he married
an Indian lady. show. So his his
successor was who was it? Saleem
Jihenir. So Jihanger was half Indian.
Now I suppose if Jenir married an Indian
lady, his son Shah Jan would be
threequarters Indian. So he would look
more Indian than Turk. And so many of
the Muggal emperors had kings had Indian
wives but they never became culturally
Indian. They may have started looking
Indian as the generations went by but
they culturally remained Turkey. Why is
that? That's a big question. Why is
that? And why? Since they adopted
Persian so so readily, why didn't they
adopt Indian culture the same way?
Because there's a barrier. Indian
culture isn't Islamic.
You can't adopt a non-Islamic culture.
Persian Persian was already the Persian
culture was already Islamic. It was
already a part of the Islamic world. So
see what happened in Persia is that
Persia got Islamized in a matter of
years.
India was various parts of India were
under Turk occupation, Arabic occupation
whatever for like close to a millennium
some parts of India those never became u
Islamized completely except for Gandhar
except for Gandhar and even in Gandhar
which is Afghanistan today you still had
Hindus and and and Afghans until until
the end of the 20th century you still
have some some some sorry not Afghan six
you still possibly have sick people in
in Gandha in Afghanistan today. I'm not
sure if there are still any but u even
in the 21st century you had sick people
who lived in Afghan in Afghanistan and
they were not Indian Afghans they were
Afghan Indian six there were Afghan six
there were pon six right u
so India never islamized the way Persia
Islamized which is why Indian culture
was always regarded as a non-Islamic
culture right as an infidel culture and
that's why the the muggles even though
many of them were of Indian Indian
ancestry largely they still could not
see Indian culture as their culture
because we are Turks and and Indian
culture is non-Islamic so how can we
adopt Indian culture so Indian culture
did creep in everywhere
yeah it did creep in but officially they
remained non-Indian which is why I do
not consider any of the Muggal kings or
emperors as Indians Kaneshka was Indian
Akbar was not Indian he was not
Okay, that's that's my opinion. You may
not agree with me. That's okay. You have
the right to your opinion. I do not see
Akbar or Jalaludin. His name was
Jalaludin, right?
Yeah. Zahirin Babar and Hayun and then
you have Jalaludin Akbar which is very
strange because there was another
Jalaludin Jalaludin the coward who Ching
Khan was pursuing all the way to India.
So, so, so none of the muggle kings were
Indian because they never adopted Indian
culture. They never became Indian. They
remained even if they may have been born
in India, even if generations of muggles
were born in India, they still remained
outsiders. They considered themselves to
be foreigners. So you so it is not right
to call them Indians. Just being born in
in a land doesn't make you a person who
belongs to the land, right? Right, there
you have it. Okay, next question. Maybe
this question should have been taken
first. Anyhow, that's fine. So, Sharma
108x says, "How and why did the Turks
become Muslim? And why didn't the
Mongols?"
Good question. Interesting question.
Comparative history. The Turks and the
Mongols, first of all, what are their
origins? So the Turks their origin is
the Hunik peoples.
I mean for example if you look at our
history Indian history uh the Huns
attempted multiple invasions of India
wave after wave of invasion of India
during the second half of the time
period of the Gupta Empire.
uh and they were called the white huns
the schwa hunas and the huns were
attempting this invasion of India at the
same time when they were invading Rome
so that's how widespread the the huns
were and what was the origin of the huns
the origin of the huns was in the land
that we now call Mongolia so the Mongol
people and the hunik people are
essentially they have the same ancestry
the same origin what's the word for
human being in the Mongol language today
hunu
Okay. Or who? So,
so there is that. So, the Mongols and
the Hones had the same ancestry. But the
Mongols, they stayed, they remained in
Mongolia. The Hones went wandering
around the world. They became nomads.
And eventually the Horns some they
conquered some parts of India. Some of
their kings were utterly nasty like
what's his name? Toramana or was it
Mihir? Mhir. No, Toraman was okay. He
built the Bameyian Buddhas. Good guy.
Good. He approves. But Mihir was an
absolute barbarian. No one liked him.
The Buddhists hated him. The Hindus
hated him. Everyone hated him. He was an
absolute atheist and a complete uh
barbarian. So Nhir was was nasty. But
the other Hunik kings were were they
became Indian. Of course. For example,
the patron of Brahagupta was a Hunik
king. Okay. His name was Vagrauk.
So the patron of the great Indian
astronomer Brahmagupta. Now anyway
coming back to the Turks. The Turks the
Horns eventually became the Turks. So
how did they became Muslim is the
question. H
so over time because of their presence
in central Asia the the Turks the Turks
let's call them Turks now they came in
contact with the Abbasid caliphate
and the the the Turks were nomads and
they were very tough hardy people
because they live in such extreme
conditions so they are naturally going
to be good warriors and they had this
practice of raiding and all that so they
were good warriors so some of The Turks
became mercenaries. They became employed
by the Abbasid caliphate. They became
soldiers in the Abbasad armies and so
on. And that's how they they discovered
Islam.
And some of them because they were
employed there and maybe they had
children there. They may have married
some local ladies or whatever, they
eventually became Islamized.
And uh somehow that kind of that's kind
of the process by which Islam spread
among the Turks.
The Turks were never conquered by the
Arabs. The Turks seem to have adopted
Islam voluntarily. That's that's as far
as I can see. Maybe I'm wrong. I have
not studied the the history in great
detail. But there was contact between
the Turks and the Abbasid
Empire or or Caliphate. The Abbasid
caliphate was from 750 AD to about 1258.
1258 is when the Mongols put a full stop
to the Abbasid Caliphate. Shri Hooligu
Khan. But we that's a different story.
So um he was Shri Ching Khan's
descendant. But that's a different
different story. So 750 AD to to 12508
AD is the Abbasid caliphate and that's
the time when you had significant
interaction between the Turks and the
Abbassads and that's how the Turks
somehow became Islamic. So the the Turks
became Muslim. Now why didn't the
Mongols become Muslim? Because they're
the same. They're the same people, same
ancestry, same heritage kind of, right?
Well, first of all, the Abbasads never
reached Mongolia.
They never did. Mongolia was was way far
away, way to the east. So there was no
Islamic presence anywhere near Mongolia.
I mean around 1000 AD for example. No
nothing. No nothing at all. No nothing
at all. And
the Turks they practiced originally the
same religion the polytheistic religion
as the Mongols which is in English
called Tingism which is a polytheistic
religion which with with multiple
deities. The two principal deities are
uh Tangri the skyfather and Umay the
earth mother. But here we have other
deities also deities also in what do you
call Tangorism. It's not monotheistic by
any means. Some people try to
mischaracterize Tangism as monotheistic
which is li which is a lie. So the Turks
were polytheists. The Mongols were also
polytheist. Same same religion. The
Mongol the Turks became Muslims. The
Mongols somehow were more resistant than
the Turks. Eventually you had um
so eventually what happened is that the
Mongol Empire became so vast, so
gigantic after a generation or two after
Chingish Khan that the western Mongol
Empire, the the the Golden Horde, the
the Ilhan etc. they
became Turkishized and they became
Islamized slowly gradually by
intermaring and and and and by by ruling
over so many Muslims it made sense for
them to become Muslim. Um so that's how
the western Mongol western expanses of
the Mongol Empire became Muslim and they
became Turkic. Then you can no longer
call them Mongols. They became Turks.
But in the Mongol Empire itself um Islam
never made made any inroads. Why is
that? There seems to have been some
significant resistance to Islam in
Mongolia among the Mongols. uh for
example we know that Shir Ching Khan has
the well he conquered half the world
and he launched his conquests because of
a sense of justice that I was wronged
and I need to u no one's going to give
me justice I need to go and get justice
myself so he had sent an embassy to the
shua the sha of karaz karazma he wanted
Mongolia to trade with karazma but the
sha Farasma had the embassy killed. He
had them beheaded. And then Chasan sends
a second embassy asking for justice. And
the Muslim guy who was part of the
embassy because you're dealing with
Muslims. He was beheaded and the others
were their heads were shaved and sent
back. So then Chinghan said, "Okay, I'm
going to go to war with you. I'm going
to smash you out of existence." And
that's what it did. So Chinghan has the
record the Islamic world hates
Chingghistan because Chingghistan killed
more Muslims than anybody has ever done
in history. Okay. Um, so maybe Chingis
Khan got developed some aversion perhaps
to Islam during his conquests of the
Islamic world. Okay. Maybe he did not
like something about it. I don't know
what it is. But uh the Chingis kind of
had this policy of of what you call
religious tolerance. He had a gigantic
empire with subjects who practiced all
kinds of religions. You obviously had
Tangism which is the Mongol religion.
You had Buddhism. You had Tibet which is
part of the Mongol Empire. You had
northern India which would have some
parts of northern India where you have
would have had Hindus also and you had a
gigantic Muslim population in the
western Mongol Empire. So
Changaskhan had given everybody the
freedom to practice the religion. You do
whatever you want. I'm not going to
interfere. There's only one thing he had
banned.
Only one thing he had banned. And Shri
Kubla Khan also continued this. He had
banned halal slaughter.
So there was something I don't know what
it was. So Changaskhan started this
practice that I will not allow halal
slaughter and Kubla Khan also continued
that. So by the time of Kubla Khan
Buddhism had become the de facto state
religion. Not officially but
unofficially it was the state religion.
Um
but this practice started with Chingish
Khan not with Kubla Khan. So even during
Kubla Khan's time he was the emperor of
China by the way Kubla Khan Chingish
Khan's grandson. So even during
Kublhan's time everything was allowed.
You could practice anything you want any
religion but the practice of halal
slaughter was not allowed. So I don't
know the reason the cause for that but
the Mongols did not allow that and uh
yeah so they had a much more vigorous
resistance to Islam compared to the
Turks who readily ab adopted it. You
won't find Islam in Mongolia today
except for some people who are not
Mongols who may practice it. a small
minority of people like the Kazaks or
whatever but you won't find Mongols
practicing Islam. Mongols will practice
practice a syncratic religion which is a
mixture a combination of Tangism and
Buddhism. That's what you what Mongols
practice today.
Rahul Dunak says historically Indian
swordsmen used a curved sword the Talvar
sword right from the Mahabharat times to
Chhatraati. We don't know about Babar at
times how the kind of what kind of
swords we had. But Chhatrapati Shivaji's
time. Yes. Of course. Yeah. Uh the
Japanese samurai swords, the katanas are
also slightly curved. But the Roman
sword, the medieval, the swords that
medieval European warriors used, these
were straight swords like a Christian
cross. Which among them were the best
considering the sharpness, weight, type
of metal and balance? Okay. Interesting
question. Really interesting question.
So if you look at the Rajput swords, the
Marata swords, these are curved blades.
Talvars, right? Talvwar swords, curved
say, curved blades. Even if you look at
um the Japanese katana, the Japanese
katana is doesn't have the exact same
curvature as the Indian Talwar sword.
It's slightly longer. It's slightly
thinner and it's got a more subtle
curvature. It's a slightly curved sword.
It's not a significantly curved curved
sword and the metal is also different.
So the Indian swords they use carbon
steel which is what the west now calls
Damascus steel but the Damascus steel
was imported from India by the way. So
it's Indian steel. So it's it's a high
quality steel and the curvature of the
sword is designed for slashing motions.
slashing, not poking, not that, but
slash slash especially from horseback.
So these curved swords swords were great
for slashing from horseback, slashing at
infantry, for example, or maybe even
other horsemen, that sort of thing.
And the Indian swords were pretty light
actually, the Talvwar swords, 1 kilo,
1.2 kilos, around that that kind of
weight. Not heavy at all. So it's I mean
yeah when you're fighting for like 3
hours 4 hours straight 1 kilo becomes
100 kilos but that's why you have to be
a warrior it's not for everyone
so the the swords are pretty light 1
kilo 1.2 2 kilo. If you go to museums
and you see the swords, okay, you you
can go to a museum and find those talwar
swords there. The first thing when I saw
that saw examples of these swords was
how small the hilts were. It's like
people were the smaller at the time.
Like my hand won't fit in. I mean, I
don't know if the swords that I saw in
that m the museum were were display
pieces of what it was, but it's like how
on earth do you grip that? You can't put
your hand in there. Uh anyway, so the
swords were pretty light, 1 kilo to 1.2
kilos. And uh the Japanese katana is
about 1.2 to 1.5 kilos. So it's kind of
somewhat heavier like 20 30% heavier
than the Indian talvar sword, but it's
got such kind of such a balance that it
feels very light. So it kind of feels
lighter than what it actually is. That's
that's the the thing about the Japanese
katana. Okay. Uh and the Japanese katana
is also used for for slashing motions.
Slashing motions, not for poking
motions. U that sort of thing. So that's
the Japanese katana.
That sort of slashing thing. Even the
English uh even the Indian talvar
slashing motions. When it comes to the
Roman sword, the Roman sword is called
the gladius.
The gladius. And what do you call
someone who uses a gladius? A gladiator.
Do you understand the origin of the term
gladiator?
A person who wields the gladius. So the
Roman sword was perfectly straight.
Straight.
And it was used the Romans used the the
the thrusting motion, not the slashing
motion. Of of course it was a
double-bladed sword. So you could use it
with slashing motions. But the primary
means of using the primary way of using
the sword, the gladius was the thrusting
motion. And that's something each each
Roman soldier was trained at, you know,
how to thrust. Uh, and that's what
differentiated the Romans from other uh
the Roman soldiers from from other
warriors and various other swords in
Europe. They kind of have continued the
tradition of the gladius, the gladius,
that sort of thing. So yeah, and and and
they were all made from different steel.
So they all were used in different ways.
So the gladius, the gladius was used for
fighting face to face, hand-to-hand
fighting, fighting in close combat, not
from horseback. That's what the Gladius
was was used for. And the the British
long sword was used by knights on
horseback and that they used it kind of
like
u kind of like a lance like like a
javelin or sometimes you could use it
use it two-handed sort of thing. But it
was not something that was agile like
the French AP for example. The French AP
is super light. It's something that you
use in in u that Olympic sore, right? Uh
the Olympics sport called fencing.
That's the French AP. It's a super
flexible kind of thing. Well, today's
today's AP is is that way, super
flexible. Historically, it wasn't that
that flexible. So, each of these weapons
served a different purpose. Some were
more flexible, some had better balance,
some had more resilience, and some were
lighter, some were heavier, and so on.
Uh but we have to remember that the
sword is like the sword is the
equivalent of of the guitar in music.
What do I mean by that?
People think of music as something that
you need the guitar for, right? But
there's so much music that doesn't
involve any guitars. But the guitar is
the cool instrument in music right now.
Similarly, the sword seems to be the
cool instrument. Like without a sword,
you can't fight. But it's not like it's
the only weapon that soldiers carry.
Many soldiers never carried swords. Some
of their some of them carried spears,
some of them carried daggers. Some of
them carried, if you look at the
Japanese, the shuriken, that's a ninja
weapon, of course. U some people carried
axes. We called it the parachu in
Sanskrit, the axe, right?
There's the bow and arrow. That's
another great weapon, right? So, it's
not like the sword is the only weapon
that can be used in warfare. You can
have soldiers who have never touched the
sword and they are great, great
soldiers, great warriors. Uh so that's
something you have to keep in mind.
That's the that's larger context that we
have to think about in warfare. And of
course in today's warfare no one carries
swords because obsolete now aren't they?
Right. Next question. Hy penguin says
why did a naser send lowquality copper?
[Music]
Who is a nasir? Yeah. So what hensing is
talking about is the world's the world's
oldest recorded customer complaint.
Let me show you what I mean by that. I
will not mention a naser but I shall put
this on the screen and I'll I'll Google
for world's oldest customer complaint.
World's oldest
customer
complaint.
So the compla the person who has written
the complaint his name is Nani. He is an
ancient Mesopotamian customer and he and
he has done a I mean he's he's purchased
copper from a merchant called Ayanasir
and this goes back to about 1750 BC. So
there's this complaint tablet to Aasir
that was excavated in the city of Ur.
It's it was written around 1750 BC. As
always, a statutoic uh warning.
Wikipedia is not necessarily a good
source of knowledge information
especially for Indian topics. But this
is fine. So this is the complaint
letter. It's a small letter. It's not
huge. It's not something that you to
carry on horseback. It's a small small
thing. Yeah. This sort of thing. And
this is a customer complaint. So Nani
the customer he had sent his servant to
meet this merchant called Ayanasir and u
he had sent money with his servant and
uh the servant handed over the money to
Ayanasir
and u the deal was that Ayanasir will
then take the money and sent and send a
consignment of highquality copper ingots
copper metal pieces
to Nani. So Nani sent his sent his
servant his his guy his his minion to go
and hand over the money and formalize
the the the sale.
So what happened eventually is that Ayan
Nasir who was a copper merchant he sent
a consignment of copper to Nani but
there was lowgrade copper
their agreement was high quality copper
but took the money and sent the say the
the agreed upon quantity of lowgrade
copper not not high-grade copper the
quantity was correct but the grade was
poor so so Nani is upset of course and
uh he writes a letter this is the letter
that I showed you. He writes a letter
and he complains in the letter that
first of all you were rude to my to my
servant. There was no need for that.
What was the need? Why do you to be rude
to my guy? Secondly, you took the money
and you gave me inferior grade copper. I
have no use for it. I need high quality
copper for my business. So, I have we
have I have given you the money, but the
sale is not concluded. That's what he is
saying. You're going to take this back.
You're going to send me the right the
right quality of copper. That's what
this letter is all about. It's a
dispute. It's a complaint. He's
complaining about the poor treatment of
his servant and is complaining about the
poor grade of the copper he received.
And he's saying that this sale is not
complete. I have given you the money,
but I've not received what I've paid
for. So, you've got to do what? You've
got to send me the right grade of
copper. After that, what happened? We
have no idea.
We have no idea because we don't have a
follow-up. We don't have a follow-up any
any follow-up to this. I mean it's not
an email thread, email email uh thread
or whatever you call it right that you
can see what happened at various dates.
So we don't know how this matter was
resolved or not whether it was resolved
or not and how it was resolved but it's
the oldest known customer complaint.
It's in the city of Ur in Mesopotamia
around the year 1750 BC. Very
interesting. So why did send lowquality
copper? Maybe he was a crook. Maybe he
was trying to to cut corners,
you know. Maybe maybe Nani lived far far
away and that's why he had to send a
servant. Maybe they're not in the same
city, so it doesn't matter. Maybe he
lives in a different kingdom. My kingdom
is a is a supplier of copper and maybe
he he lives in a kingdom where there's
less copper. So they need to buy it from
me. Then what you going to do now?
You're going to send your king with an
army. Why are you looking to that? He's
on good terms with my king. That sort of
thing. So we don't know what happened at
the end. But yeah, very interesting.
kind of funny if you read it now. It
must be really infuriating when it
happened. It would not be funny at all
when it happened. But today, we can all
have a laugh at these people's expense,
especially poor Nani. He sent the money,
he did everything right, and he got low
quality copper. Obviously, he'll be
upset about that, right?
So, the the villain of the story is this
this guy Anasir.
Okay. Okay, Amish Aisha says um why did
Zoroastrianism, ancient Egyptian
religions, ancient Greek/ Roman
religions and old Norse religions
almost get totally destroyed but why not
Judaism? Interesting question. Uh it is
true that ancient Zoroastriism I mean
not ancient but Zoroastrianm itself
almost got wiped out.
Today you have a few Zoroastrians who
still survive in Persia in in Iran and
you have a larger but declining
population of Zoroastrians who live in
India who have been in India for about
1100 years or so more than a thousand
years uh and their ancestors came from
Persia about a thousand plus years ago.
Oh, and and and and you also have newer
Zorastians who came about a couple of
centuries ago from to India after they
discovered that that older Zorashians
have been staying in India for a
thousand years. The some more Zorastians
came in recently like in the past couple
of hundred years or something. The
Iranian cafes and all those people they
they are the newer migrants to India,
Paris, Zoroastrians. So, Zoroastrianism
is almost wiped out right in its in its
original homeland Persia. Ancient
Egyptian religion entirely gone. Not a
trace survival.
No one practices it today. Completely
wiped out of existence. The ancient
Greek religion completely gone. Nothing
survives. Ancient Roman religion,
absolutely nothing survives whatsoever.
No one practices it today. Old Norse
religion, well, it was wiped out more
recently. No one practices the old Norse
religion today. But people are kind of
trying Nordic revival religions like
Asatro which kind of worships the old
gods Thor, Odin and and so on but they
do it in a kind of modern way. It's not
the old Norse religion. It's a revival
religion. It's not a continuation of the
old Norse religion.
So all these religions were always were
wiped out apart from zostinism which
kind of still survives in small number
in small populations. So why did all
these religions get obliterated?
Zoros religion not quite but still. But
why not Judaism? Why did Judaism survive
is the question. Well, you to ask
yourself what obliterated
these religions. These are all
polytheistic religions by the way. And
now some some very intelligent people
are going to say yeah this Abhijit
always lies. Now he's claiming
Zoroastinism is polytheistic. See
another lie of Cha is caught. That what
that's what they will say. Let me show
you something. There are many people who
try to portray Zoroastrianism as
u um a monotheistic religion. Let's see
what the the Wikipedia itself has to
say. Wikipedia is not a reliable source
of information. Right? Let's see what it
says. Zoroastrianism.
Let us see what Wikipedia has to say
about Zoroastrianism.
All right.
Um Darosi etc.
Zoratosama.
No first. No that's okay. That's all
right. So opinions vary among scholars
as to whether Zorostism is monotheistic,
polytheistic, kenotheistic or
combination of all three. That's fine.
Okay. I don't care about someone's
opinions. Let's look at the facts. So
let's go down. Ethmology, theology,
nature of the divine. Okay. Look here.
Look at what what Wikipedia says.
Zoroastronism contains multiple classes
of divine beings. What is a divine
being? It's a god, right? Multiple
classes of gods who are typically
organized into tiers and spheres of
influence. The ahuras,
they are a class of gods inherited by
zostinism from the prehistoric
Indo-Iranian religion. What was this
prehistoric indooran religion in the
rigida? Oh, the book one of the books of
this prehistoric Indo-aranian religion
was a rigida. I see
the ancient religion of Persia was
Hinduism. Okay. They are they they are
forced to accept it in Wikipedia. Um
where here here indirectly indirectly
they are not saying that they they're
calling it the prehistoric Indo-Iranian
religion. What prehistoric means before
1 AD right? Even Zorost is is
prehistoric then
and and then they're mentioning the
rigida because that's the only source of
knowledge they have now right so in the
riged assura denotes the older gods and
and vitra mitra veruna etc they are
assuras yes so the assuras are a class
of gods in zoroastranism then you have
the greatest of the assuras the ahuram
mazda right of course then you have
auroritra or mitra mitra vun come on
mitra then you have the yazatas divine
beings worshiped by song and sacri
sacrifice. What were the so-called
sacrifices? Yasnas which is the same as
our yajnas.
All right. So zor zoroastrinism is not a
a monotheistic religion. Here Wikipedia
itself is saying that they have
different class of divine beings but
they are using the term divine being so
that they don't have to use the word god
because if you use the word god then
you're taking a stance. They are saying
it's polytheistic. We want to keep it
vague deliberately vague. So we'll say
various classes of divine beings.
Now in Christianity they will say there
also there are divine beings. There are
angels and demons. There's Lucifer the
bringer of light and demons may be evil
but angels are good right but they're
not god. They only slightly divine
beings. So that way in zash also also
you have auras assuras and all. They're
like angels. They're not really gods.
That's the kind of obfiscation these
people will do. The fact is very clear.
Zoroastrianism
is a polytheistic religion. And today
even Zoroastrianism Zoroastrians
themselves will will oppose this. Some
of them. No no no no no. We only believe
in aura mazda
and angramen and all these ahuras and
zatas and all they're like they're like
spirits or or angels in Christianity.
It's it's monotheistic. Many Zoroastrian
Zoroastrians themselves do this. Now I
have no idea why. Whatever the fact is
that Zoroastrianism is a polytheistic
religion. So was ancient Egyptian
religion. So was ancient Greek religion.
So was ancient Roman religion. So was
the old Norse religion. So was entire
Europe's culture.
And all of that was destroyed by what?
by one out of two by either of the two
major Abrahamic religions, Islam or
Christianity. So, Zoro Zoroastrianism,
what a complicated thing to say, tongue
twister for me. My tongue doesn't work
fine. Zoroastrianism
was wiped out by Islam to a large
extent.
Um, ancient Egyptian religion was wiped
out by Islam to a to a complete extent.
It was obliterated.
Ancient Greek religion was wiped out by
Christianity. Ancient Eg Roman religion
was wiped out by Christianity. Ancient
Nordic religion was wiped out by
Christianity. It's one of the two
Abrahamic religions that has wiped out a
polytheistic religion.
Judaism is the original Abrahamic
religion.
So that won't be wiped out. Right? Of
course, today you have a conflict
between the the the Jews and the
Muslims. That's that's a whole different
story. And apparently it is it is said
that the prophet of the Muslims had some
animosity perhaps towards the Jews. I'm
not sure I don't know about the history
in any detail but that's kind of the
sense that I get. Uh so yeah so Judaism
is not a polytheistic religion. It's the
original Abrahamic religion and that's
why you can't wipe that out, right? You
can't polytheistic cultures and
religions. It's okay. Fair game.
All right. Uh okay two questions about
essentially the same topic. Rudra Gulba
says it is said that humans contain some
amount of genes from Neanderthalss. Is
there a chance of some interbreeding
that might have happened and why? And
Amisha says why are homo sapiens and
Neanderthals Neanderthalss considered to
be separate species? What could be the
reason that the Neanderthal DNA is found
in modern humans? Do did humans and
Neanderthalss interbreed with each
other? Does Neanderthal DNA come from
both males and females? Very interesting
questions. First of all, uh many people
believe that humans and Neanderthalss
are separate species. So I can
understand the confusion completely. The
fact is that we are subspecies. We are
not different species. We are
subspecies. Now I'm going to compare it
with other species. And if it um upsets
somebody, don't be upset. Okay? So for
example,
I love to talk about other species as a
comparative measure. So don't be upset
that I'm comparing humans humans with
animals.
It's just a comparison for illustrative
purposes. This is a scientific
discussion. All right? So think about
man's best friend, the dog, and think
about his cousin, the wolf. We have so
many species. I mean so many different
kinds of wolves on the planet. We have
the Indian wolf, right? Uh what's the
what's the wolf's name in in the jungle
book? Aa, right? Mowgli's Mowgli's clan
or whatever. Aa wolf wolf clan.
So we have the Indian wolf, we have the
Himalayan wolf, we have the European
wolf, we have the So wolf wolf is a is a
it's a species of of animal, right? And
the dog the dog is a subspecies of the
wolf. It's not a separate species. The
dog and the wolf are the same species
but different subspecies. So the dog and
the wolf can interbreed and they can
have children offspring which are the
same species once again. So the dog and
the wolf are the same species. Similarly
humans and near the homo sapiens and
near the tiles we're also the same
species but different subspecies. Okay.
So
for example, lion and tiger,
they are different species. They can
interbreed,
but I'm not sure if their offspring are
are fertile. Maybe they are sterile. I'm
not sure. Horse and donkey can
interbreed, but their offspring is mule,
which I think is sterile. It's not
fertile. It can't have offspring of its
own. Uh but humans and neanderals
uh they did interbreed and their
offspring were not sterile. They were
they fertile. They were able to pass on
their genes which means that humans and
neanderals were genetically very very
close. Same species maybe separate
subspecies.
Uh so yes interbing did happen. Now
don't ask me why. That's that's a
choice. It's a pref personal choice.
People have choices and people make
choices as to what kind of partner you
want to have and don't question the
choices. Same species, you can do it.
Okay. Okay. This is a really funny topic
somehow.
So why it happened? Don't ask me why. I
don't know the motivations. But uh our
ancestors, human, I mean homo sapiens
ancestors, they came out of Africa about
80,000 years ago. Maybe 85,000 years
ago, maybe 60,000 years ago. We don't
know exactly when the out of Africa
migration happened but that's the best
uh theory that we have that there was an
out of Africa migration that gave rise
to the modern homo sapiens population.
So when this out of Africa migration
happened, you had Neanderthalss who
already lived in Eurasia
and they may have emerged out of Africa
maybe maybe half a million years before
homo sapiens, maybe 700,000 years before
homo sapiens, but we were still still
sufficiently close enough genetically
that we are we were still the same
species. So if you look at depictions of
of Neanderthals, they are depicted as
really ugly and hideous creatures. Maybe
they were not that ugly and hideous.
Maybe they were good-looking people. Who
knows? Uh so there was some kind some to
some extent there was inbreeding
interbreeding. Sorry, not inbreeding,
interbreeding between homo sapiens and
Neanderthalss. Uh do we carry? So the
consequence of that is that even though
the Neanderthalss have ceased to exist
as a separate subspecies,
they haven't gone entirely extinct
because most
non-African people carry some
Neanderthal DNA which means most
non-African people have some Neanderthal
ancestry which means that there is some
Neanderthal blood in you. It means that
nanatal DNA is not extinct.
So what's the percentage of DNA? Maybe
around 4% 5%. It's like having one great
if if one parent is nandal 50, right?
50%. If one grandparent it's 25. If one
great grandparents it's 12.5.
If one great great grandparents it's so
it's about having like one great great
grandparent who was nanderthal. it. So
it's it's not going to be really visible
that you will not have bigger bones or
bigger brows or like whatever but it's
going to be subtle. So all the all the
good uh traits beneficial traits that
would be beneficial for survival you
will have absorbed them and you would
carry them without knowing that it's
nandal DNA. Um yeah so and it is said
that in India now this is the funny part
out of all the non-African humans
Indians I believe as uh from what I know
carry the least amount of nandthal DNA
why I don't know maybe why maybe I can
tell you why let's go to the map
okay let me open the map and let's let's
examine the map to understand why
Indians carry the least amount of
neanderal DNA in all the non-African
humans. Why is that? Let's let's find
out once again. Uh let me uh hide the
question for a second. Let us embigen
this.
Uh this is better. Yeah. So the out of
Africa migration probably happened
around here here the straight of Bab
al-Mandde.
Okay. Okay. So they crossed over here
the African ancestors of all non-African
humans and then right now it's all
desert everywhere Yemen, Oman but at
that time whenever this this this uh
migration happened along the coastline
you would see green. You can see some
small patches of green here right? Some
small patches of green. Little bit of
vegetation is there. If you look at the
satellite image you can see some
vegetation. So at that time the entire
coastline like this was just barely
green to be able to somehow support a
small number of people. So they traveled
all the way northwards along the Arabian
Peninsula
and probably somewhere here they crossed
again the straight of Hormuz and then
the further over here also you probably
had
greenery along the coastline. So they so
they kept on following the greenery
until they reached the Indian
subcontinent
which was entirely green
super fertile it could it could support
any kind of human population in the
millions if you needed so that's where
homo sapiens first settled down and
eventually when they were all rested
after a few thousand years and all they
said okay let's go wandering because
that's the nature of homo sapiens and
from here from India from the
subcontinent they spread out in all
directions and during This journey from
Bab al- Mandeb along the the coast of
Arabia
after crossing the straight of Hormos
and going eastwards there were no
Neanderthalss in that region. Neandthals
are found in present day Israel in
present day Anatolia in yeah the western
part of Eurasia but not really in the
subcontinent or or near the subcontinent
which is why before they came to India
they did not en encounter any
Neanderthalss but only when they
expanded out of India at a later date
and went westwards that's when they
encountered Neanderthalss and interbred
with Neanderthalss which is why people
who live in the western regions they
have like 4% or something Neanderthal
ancestry while Indians have negligible
Neanderthal ancestry. So unless for
example if you take me my ancestry is
mainly from western India which means
that I would most likely not have any
Neanderthal ancestry unless I have
ancestors who are Arian invaders.
So the only way I can have nearal
ancestry if is if my ancestors were the
evil white-skinned Arian invaders.
Yeah. And some people tell me I look
like an arian invader. So maybe
so anyway. So that's the deal with the
Neanderthals, right? Uh does last
question by Amisha is that does
Neianderal DNA um come from both males
or females? I'm not sure I know the
answer to that. That's an interesting
question. I suppose it would come from
both. Uh do we have um is it is it like
what kind of DNA do we have? Is it
autotosomal DNA? Is it somatic DNA? Is
it is it sex chromosome DNA?
Not sure about that. I'll have to look
into that. That's an interesting
question.
Right. Next.
Amisha says, "What's the difference
between race and ethnicity?" Okay, race
and ethnicity. Look
um see first of all race and ethnicity
these are not scientific terms. You
can't define these two terms precisely
but they are used in different contexts.
For example when you talk about race
okay the race race is is a is a western
uh concept. The westerners after they
became all powerful in the past 500
years they created the idea of like four
five six races. the the Caucasian race,
the the African race,
the the Mongolian race, the Oustraloid
race,
and um I don't know,
I I'm not sure what other races may
exist. Uh so that's race. It's based on
just broad skin color.
uh so someone like me they would
consider me to be somewhere on the
intersection in the ven diagram of the
oustrloid and and coccasian race
uh if if it's somebody from from Sweden
or whatever they would consider them to
be pure coauasin if it's somebody from
for example an Australian aboriginal
people they'll say you are you're
Oustraloid
if it is somebody from Mongolia or China
they will say you are Mongaloid but if
it's somebody from Indonesia they'll say
you a mixture of oustraloid and
mongaloid and that sort of thing you
know so and if you if you're from Africa
they'll say you're you're what yeah it
was the nword negroid which was the term
that they used to use the racist
Europeans not we them uh so that is race
that's based on very broad skin color
classifications and there were some
other nuances like prenology uh study of
brain size and shape and no skull size
and shape and god knows what else that
is race. Okay, there is no such thing as
race or pure race or anything. There's
no such thing even as a pure species
actually, but that's a different story.
Now, what is ethnicity? Ethnicity is
like a more granular perception of race.
So, if you look at the Balkan region,
the Balkans in Europe for example,
this is the Balkan region. We'll we'll
go go there. This region here, if you
find Greece, then go northwest of
Greece. Northwest. So this region here,
Serbia, Bosnia, Herzuggavina, U,
Croatia, Slovenia, Montenegro, Kosovo,
Kosovo. Okay, we will not discuss
Kosovo. It's controversial. Albania,
North Macedonia, and so on. Bulgaria.
Okay, not Bulgaria, but all of this is
is a Balkans region. Okay, now I suppose
the people of the Balkans consider
themselves to have different
ethnicities.
Maybe they're all the white race
perhaps, but different ethnicities. I am
not a Serb. I am a Kosovar.
No, I am not Serb. I am Montenegron.
I am not Montenegron. I am Bosnian. No,
I'm not Bosnjak. I'm Croatian. Croatian.
You Croatians, I am Slovenian. Now, all
of you are are wrong. We the Albanians
are number one and so on. These are
different ethnicities.
Same people overall, the same race so to
say, white people, but different
ethnicities. The Greeks in Greece they
are they have Greek ethnicity. We are
not Balkans. No, we are not like you and
we are not Turks. The Turks are like no
we not Greeks. The Turks are extremely
allergic to Greece because the Turks
have Greek ancestry, don't they?
But they consider themselves to have
different ethnicity. We are the Turk
people.
So ethnicity is more granular compared
to race. Uh if you look at the
subcontinent for example uh if you
disregard the arian dravidian nonsense
then Indians are one ethnicity
which would include the Pakistanis,
Bangladeshies
and there'll be some people who will
disagree no they'll say no no no
everybody is different ethnicity the
gujaratis are different ethnicity from
the Assam the Bengalis are different
ethnicity from the udyas so whichever
way say there is no definition you see
you can Make it as complicated as you
want or as simple as you want. But the
ethnicity is generally something that's
that's based on nations and and smaller
cultural divisions compared to something
as vast as race. Okay.
Uh Praband Das says big fan. Thank you
sir. Read two recent books. Thank you
very much. Thank you very much. They
were tremendously good. Oh thank you so
much even more. My question is can
nuclear weapons be destroyed making them
unimpactful? Now you all may ask me how
is this a historical question?
Well, I'll I'll bring history into this.
Very simple. Have nuclear weapons been
destroyed in the past? Let's say in the
20th century, if we discuss 20th
century, we're discussing history now.
Right. Right.
So, have nuclear weapons been destroyed
in the past? I recently, maybe a week
ago or so, I don't know when it was, I
did an 8 hour live stream after which I
forgot everything I did in the past. It
wiped my memory clean. So I don't
remember when I discussed this but uh I
recently kind of remembered that I spoke
about the Cuban missile crisis and I had
mentioned at the time that during the
Cuban missile crisis which happened in
1962 the United States had about 25,000
nuclear warheads. How many? 25,000
nuclear warheads. How many did the USSR
have? About 3 three and a half thousand.
three three and a half thousand nuclear
warheads the USSR had at the time.
Then
today if you look at the the balance the
Americans have 5,000 something and the
Russians have about 500 or thousand
more. So today it is much lower than
those thresholds.
So what happened to those 25,000 nuclear
warheads? Something was done to them.
Right? For example, in 19, excuse me,
which year was it? Was it 1991? You had
something called the start treaty. Start
strategic arms reduction treaty. Let's
Google, let's Google it.
So I believe in 1985 there was a summit
between um
Reagan
Reagan Gore
Gorbachev
summit
summit in Geneva 85. Yes I know because
I was there at the time. So this was a
summit that happened in Geneva because
they wanted a neutral venue. Mr. Gurbach
had just become the leader of Russia and
they had a summit over if I recall
correctly two days or two days they had
a summit and they had some discussions
where you had a whole bunch of minions
present and they had some discussions
where you did not have anyone except for
the two of them and this was the
beginning of the u you could say the
between the two countries to some extent
and one of the consequences of this uh
summit that they had was the 1991 it
took five six years 1991
Start treaty start start one treaty the
first treaty to require the reduction of
strategic nuclear weapons was signed in
1991 by the US and the USSR reducing
each country's stockpile by a third. The
treaty was a result of nine years of
negotiation. So the Gorbachev Reagan
summit in Geneva was part of that
and they established a framework
comprehensive framework for the
reduction deep region reduction and
strategic arms. U
so uh the start treaty if you look at
the the essence of essence of the treaty
the treaty barred its signaries from
deploying more than 6,000 nuclear
warheads and a total of 1,600 ICBMs and
bombers. Okay, so that was a start
treaty. So, the Americans went from
25,000 plus nuclear warheads to about
5,000 something today.
If they if they are telling the truth, I
suppose they are. So, what happened to
those nuclear weapons? Those nuclear
warheads, what happened to them?
Obviously, they were dismantled, right?
They were totally dismantled. So, how do
you dismantle a nuclear warhead? A
nuclear warhead is essentially it has it
has a design. It has components. For
example, you have the design the teller
teller ulum design. What is it? Let's
see. Let's hydro that's a hydrogen bomb
design. Thermonuclear
ulam. Yeah, teller ulum design. It's an
implosion design. There is trium. Is it
what was it? Uh boosted fusion primary
and then there's a secondary fusion
secondary. This is spark fishable spark
plug. So as you can see you have facile
material that is arranged in a certain
way and kept in specific parts of the
warhead. All you have to do is open up
the warhead and take out the facile
material very carefully and ensure it
never comes in contact and never uh
becomes uh critical mass or it never
goes critical or supercritical. That's
it. Then you can dismantle the whole
thing and it becomes completely
harmless.
So it's it's absolutely feasible. It can
be done. Okay, there you have it.
Swapnil Mishra says, "How did Robert
Mugab's policies towards Zimbabwe's
white population affect the country's
economy? And in what ways were his
actions comparable to Idi Amin's
treatment of foreigners in Uganda?"
Interesting comparison. Idi Amin Robert
Mugab. Idi Amin 1960s 1970s. Robert
Mugabe late 80s all the way to the n to
the 2010s
I think Robert Mugabe was deposed in
2017 2018 2019 around that time pretty
recent but he came to power I mean he he
was a big deal in the 1970s but he
became the president in 1980 something
maybe 85 87 around that time okay so if
you want to look at I mean if you want
to see what the two gentleman's looked
like uh you have Robert Mugabe
Mugabe. Robert Mugab.
So that's Mr. Robert Mugab.
He was the president for a very long
time. He's passed away now I believe.
And then you have the other great
gentleman Idyiamin.
There is Mr. Idi Amin.
So they both had kind of similar
policies but they had different
ideologies.
uh Idi Amin was not a communist. Robert
Mugabi was a communist, socialist,
whatever you want to call him.
Uh so what so first of all let's talk
about Uganda and Idyamin. What is
Uganda? We go to we go to Africa. Yes.
And we go to Eastern Africa, Lake
Victoria. That's where we will find Enbe
and Uganda. So let's do it.
Here
is the map. Now we are in India. Yes. So
we go to the south of India. We cross
the equator. We go into the Indian
Ocean. Then we go westwards and we reach
east Africa. In East Africa at the Horn
of Africa we have Somalia. We go south.
We have Kenya. Nice country. We go
further south Tanzania. And then we go
northwest of Tanzania. In east of Kenya
where you have Uganda, you have Kala,
you have Enbe. So this is the country
where Shri Robert Shri Idi Amin dada uh
that's the country he ruled and the
terrible thing he did is that he
expelled the Indians from Uganda
I think around 197172 I think it was the
year after the Bangladesh war which
which makes it 1972
so it is in 1972 that I am a expelled
all Indians from Uganda he said that
these people are parasites they have
captured our entire economy.
We need to liberate our economy from
these parasites and give the jobs, give
give the businesses back to Africans.
Why was was he saying this?
So in 197172
Indians were about 1% of Uganda's
population. Indians have had a presence
in Eastern Africa for thousands of
years. Okay? mainly people from Gujarat
and western India who were trading
with u the various kingdoms in East
Africa. Uh I'll not go into detail in
that. So Uganda you had about 1% Indian
population. I don't know what the
population of Uganda was was at the time
but 1% of that was Indians. Very small
number of Indians. But here's the deal.
And by the way, Indians owned 90% of
Uganda's businesses and they paid 90% of
Uganda's tax.
So then the logic went is that these
people have captured everything.
They have deprived
ordinary Ugandans of any opportunity.
This 1% micro minuscule minority, they
have taken over everything because they
are so violent, right? And Indians
violent really. So but Indians owned 90%
of the businesses and paid 90% of the
tax. So Idi expelled Indians from
Uganda.
What was the consequence? So after
expelling Indians from Uganda, he handed
over all these businesses that were
owned by Indians to native Ugandans, not
Indians, not Indian origin people, but
native Ugandans. And the consequence of
that was that all the businesses
crashed.
The native Ugandans for whatever reason
did not did not have the ability to run
the businesses. So all the businesses
failed.
Uganda went into a went into a
recession. The economy crashed.
Inflation rose
and u
Uganda's manufacturing sector
disappeared because Indians were doing
manufacturing.
So it was a disaster for Uganda's
economy. The Indians were not depriving
the natives of of business of business
opportunities. The Indians were the only
ones who knew how to run the businesses
and that's why they were running all the
businesses. They were not Indians were
not invaders who came with arms, right?
They came peacefully and established
themselves and created these industries
and businesses. Indians created these
industries and businesses. But after a
few generations, nobody remembers that
the Indians have created this. Now they
will be they will say that you stole it
from us. So the Indians were expelled
and the Ugandan economy crashed. The
Ugandan Ugandan manufacturing sector
crashed
and it's never really recovered from
that. Afterwards, the Indians were
brought back. They were allowed back.
But I'm not sure if it made a huge
difference after uh later on.
So that's the example of Uganda. Okay,
it was a disaster for the country, for
its economy, for its manufacturing
sector. Now when Mr. Robert Mugab became
the dictator, so both are dictators.
Okay. So Mr. Mugabi became director of
Zimbabwe. Zim where is Zimbabwe. We look
at Zimbabwe now. Yes.
So we were looking at Uganda. Yes. So
now so we were here on the northern
shore of this lake that they call in
Lake Victoria. And there's a lake Albert
also.
Uh anyway you you come back s further
south. You go south of Tanzania. You go
south of Malawi Mambique. Zambia and we
have Zimbabwe. Zimbabwe is a country
that's that has a shared border with
South Africa. Now all Indians know where
South Africa is. So now we can locate
it. This is Zimbabwe. So Mr. uh Robert
Mugab
became the dictator of Zimbabwe around
1980 something 87 perhaps
and he ruled the country with an iron
fist for until what 2018 2019 2017
somewhere around that time. So
it's a 30 40 years whatever it is 30
years.
So now
Zimbabwe used to be ruled by British
origin white people. It was called
Rhdesia.
It was named after Cecil Roads, a
notorious uh colonialist colonial
colonial colonialist
who did all kinds of horrific things to
Africa. Anyway, the country was called
Rudesia. It was named after Cecil Roads
and eventually it became independent and
event and there was a m there was a
gentleman called Mr. Banana who was the
leader of Zimbabwe before Mr. Mugab.
His name was Mr. Banana.
I forget his first name. A very biblical
name. Let's let's let's look it up,
shall we?
Let's have some fun, right? Let's not
always be serious about learning. I
think you should have fun. So, who was
Robert Mugab's predecessor? First of
all, let's let's Google Robert Mugabe.
Let's go to his Wikipedia entry and we
will look into his predecessor. Who was
his predecessor? It's a guy called Mr.
Banana with a biblical name preceded by
not Muzura,
preceded by not Chita Pochipo.
Uh
who was okay of Zimbabwe? Who was the
first president?
Okay, so Mugabi was the first president.
Emerson Mangamak. Okay, but who who was
before Robert Mugab, leader of Zimbabwe
before Mugabi? Let me just look search
for banana.
Ah
okay. He was preceded by Kanan Banana.
Cananan.
Uh that is why is it a small small image
anyhow? So that is Mr. Banana who was
the gentleman who preceded Mr. Mugabe
and Mr. Mugabi becomes the president of
Zimbabwe
and he
what he did was he disempowered the
whites and after the year I think 2000
he took away he forcibly took away all
the farmland for from the white people
and handed it handed it over to black
people. So after even after Mr. Mugabe
became the dictator. White people
remained some white people remained in
Zimbabwe and they were primarily employ
they were primarily farmers. They owned
land large amounts of land and they did
farming
and they produced at least 40% of
Zimbabwe's agricultural output
if not more if not more at least 40% is
what I remember. Now their land is taken
away
Mr. Mugabi encourages his party's
supporters to go and forcibly take over
the land of the white people and maybe
do whatever you want with the families
whatever you know.
So once this happens all the farmland
comes into the hands of of native
Zimbabweans
and they don't know how to farm and that
caused a disastrous recession in
Zimbabwe. There was hyperinflation. the
Zimbabwe and paper currency became
cheaper than paper itself
and eventually I think they had to as a
stop cap measure use the US dollar
instead of the Zimbabwean dollar or
something and yeah so it was a disaster
once again and Zimbabwe has never really
recovered from that similarly Uganda
also never really recovered from
expelling the Indians so pretty similar
policies but done in different ways both
were pretty brutal one towards the
Indians one towards the whites and both
caused significant disasters in these
nations.
Um but when it comes to the Indians and
the whites, you can't really compare the
two. See, the whites existed in Africa
as a consequence of colonialism which
was brutal. The whites were invaders in
Africa. The Indians were not invaders.
The Indians had been trading in Africa.
that set up trade outposts in Africa
going back centuries.
Indians have had a presence in Africa
east on the east coast of of Africa for
centuries maybe thousands of years.
Africa's eastern Africa's cuisine is
Indianized. Their their the way they
dress is Indianized. Even their language
is Indianized. They eat samosas. They
eat they eat Gujarati style curries.
They they wear u the ladies wear dresses
that look like saries that have patterns
that are similar to patterns that were
printed in in that were u manufactured
in western India for centuries. So you
can see the Indian influence there. It's
not been it's not this cultural
influence would not exist if it had come
through invasion.
through invasion. When you when a
cultural influence exists, it it
generally takes the form of religion
because invaders they force the natives
to adopt the religion like the
Portuguese did in India in Goa, the
French did in in Pondicherry,
the British tried in India, the Brit and
so on. Long stories, right? The Arabs
did everywhere, but Indians didn't do
that. The the
there's no Hindu, black Hindus there as
far as I know. So you can't really
compare the two as the same thing. The
whites who were living in Zimbabwe,
their ancestors were invaders. The
Indians who were living in Uganda and
all across Eastern Africa, they were
never invaders. They came as traders and
they were allowed to settle down by the
locals and they became eventually part
of the local communities. So that's the
difference. Big difference there.
Okay. Amisha says, "If I was an everyday
Indian living under the British Raj, the
British occupation of India, how much
contact would I have would I likely have
had with uh the British people, the
British occupiers?" Well, that's a
pretty interesting question that you ask
here. And how and how do I figure it out
as a question, right? So, uh
um let's let's ask Google once again.
Let's go to our Google friend uh to our
friend Google and we shall ask a simple
question. How many
many
British
how many British occupiers were in India
during
the peak
of the occupation?
Okay. What's it say? Oh, it finds my
video. That's that's a different one.
Okay. At at its peak in 1947, the
British population of in India was about
800,000 to 1 million including civilians
and their descendants. However, the
occupying forces were much smaller
consisting of of about 20,000 British
civil and military personnel
in 1921 who were responsible for the
direct administration of the vast
territory. So the civilians if you
include the civilians it's about 1
million people okay and if you only
include the occupation forces
which is the civil and military
personnel it's 20,000
um so let's say you were living in India
during the British occupation in 1947
our population was 330 million roughly
undivided India and the British were
maximum 1 million
So it is 330 Indians to one British
person. So it's and the British would be
concentrated in the power centers. They
will not be spread across the entire
country. So if you are living in in
let's say a town or a village, you would
perhaps never see a British person in
your entire life perhaps if you were
fortunate.
But if you are living in a big city, if
you were living in what was then called
Bombay, which is now Mumbai, then you
would see British people on a regular
basis, I suppose, because there were
lots of British in Bombay, Mumbai. If
you were living in Delhi or Kolkata,
then also you would see British people
from time to time, I suppose. Um, that
sort of thing. So the British population
was at its peak about 800,000 to 1
million. That's 1947. So depending on
where you were you may you may you could
have you could potentially spend your
entire life without seeing a British
person if you were fortunate. Yeah
that's the kind of Yeah. So they had a
pretty small number of occupiers
actually just 20,000 British civilian
military personnel
makes you question a lot of things and
it it tells you how well the British
understood the nature of power.
All right. Nirvana Shanks says, "How was
Tenokitlan built on water with canals
and floating gardens different from
European cities at the time?" Okay, what
is Tokitlan?
I will show you Tanuktitlan. Yes, I
will. We have to go to maps.
So, we go to map. We zoom out from
Africa
and I shall take you to the city of
Tenokitlan.
So, we go westwards. We go westwards. We
go westwards. across the Atlantic.
Now we go northwards into central
central America. And now we zoom into
what's called Mexico.
And we zoom in. And we zoom in. And we
zoom in. This here is Toklan. It's now
called Mexico City. It used to be called
Tokitlan.
And the city was built inside a lake.
The lake was called Lake Texco.
T E X C O C O.
This was the seat of the Triple
Alliance. The Aztec trip Triple
Alliance. So the city was built inside a
lake. You can't see the lake today. The
Spaniards have wiped the lake out,
right?
And this basilica of whatever whatever
it is built on a destroyed
temple. Okay, that's what the Spaniards
do. You will see the similar things
happening in India also. Wherever you
have the old Portuguese or French
churches, they'll be built on destroyed
temples. Anyhow, so this is Mexico city.
It is it it used to be called
Tanuktitlan before the Spanish
destruction of the Aztec Empire.
Now, so how was this city of Tanuktitlan
different from European cities of the
time? So Tino Thetlan was like I said
built inside a lake. The lake wasn't
super deep and the city was built as as
like like islands kind of floating
islands inside the lake and instead of
having water I mean having having roads
you had waterways. So the city had
canals for transportation. You could
transport humans even animals on boats
in the canals. So today you if you want
to travel in in in any any major Indian
city you would take I don't know two
wheeler three-wheer four-wheeler
whatever if you don't have one of your
own you can hire taxi or whatever call
call one of the uh services you can do
that so in tinctitan you could I suppose
call a boat walla I would like to go to
so place market and come back how much
that sort of thing and you also had
causeways
so you
So that that connected the city to the
mainland which was not the lake and in
the middle of the lake where you had the
city you also had farmland. So they had
created this artificial islands kind of
floating islands where you had farms.
It was a city like no other
and it was a very powerful it was a seat
of an of an empire. So that's very
different from European cities. European
cities around 1500 were generally
constructed around forts
and castles.
So Europe was this tribal region where
you had tribal warfare that went on for
centuries
going back to the pre-Christian era.
Um so all the major cities of Europe
they started as castles and
fortifications. So you would have some
kind of chieftain, maybe a small king or
small chieftain who would construct a a
fort or a castle with a moat around it
and you will have like a 100 200
soldiers inside and because that place
is a place of protection which will give
you protection from neighboring raiders.
That's why small a small settlement will
come around it and they will offer
services to the king and the king will
offer protection and that's how the the
the the the settlement slowly grow and
that's how you have cities like Paris
and so on that became big cities
eventually and they grew these cities
like Paris etc they grew organically
even London initially they grew
organically they grew hapazarly they
were not planned cities
and uh that's why they were congested
they would they would not be very
hygienic uh They used to
they used to have a class of people
called the gong farmers who would be
allowed inside inside the city only at
night to take the off the roads
because the Europeans used to dump the
on the roads the excretita in the
night from buckets onto the streets of
the city. the streets the the cities
used to stink immensely and there was a
certain cast of Europeans who were
called the gong fermu or the gong
farmers would be who were untouchables
and who would be allowed only inside the
city at night to collect the excrement
and they have to disappear before
morning because they are untouchable
they they're dirty
and they their children could only do
this job this work they could not aspire
to any other life so that's the kind of
cast system you had in Europe so cities
in Europe were disgustingly dirty,
stinky, extremely congested. Uh in in a
city like Rome, you had something called
the Cluaka Maxi Cluaka Maxima, which was
the great sewer and you had smaller
sewers. Rome at least had sewers, but
other European cities later on did not
have sewage systems. Uh Pinoitan was not
like that. Everything was well organized
and so overall it was very different,
right? a unique city and that's
something the Spaniards completely
smashed
and and and they created they renamed it
to Mexico City and and they destroyed
the lake which is why there is no lake
there today.
Okay. Shou says how didi become uncool
in India. How can we bring it back? Doi
it became uncool like everything else
because of the British occupation and
because today western dress is the norm
in India. Western dress is cool. You
wear designer clothing, western
clothing, you're cool. You wear the
humble doti or you wear a sari with a
pettic coat and blouse, you're so you're
so uncool. You're uncool,
right? How do you make it cool? Well,
have designer do have have mix and match
your your dresses with doies. You can
wear a polo shirt and and sneakers with
doi. But not just your khadiwali doti.
You can have a silk doti designer doti.
Why not,
right? I mean, you can you can bring it
back. It's a it's a very comfortable
piece of clothing and it's it's it's
tailor made for the Indian climate. The
jeans aren't tailor made for Indian clim
for the Indian climate even though we
all wear them, right? The doies are
buties are uncool. That's why nobody
wants to wear them. But doies are really
good. They're perfect for the Indian
Indian climate. And u uh so historically
it's not like all Indians wore dies. The
Kushans when they conquered northern
India they brought in a different kind
of attire what's now called Salvoir
Kamse the Kushans used to wear the
Salvar kamies kind of thing they used to
wear boots and and trousers which have
now become the salvoir
u but even that is light and airy right
it's not like tight
um so the doti can be made cool again
let me give you an example of a of an
ancient historical doi from my Instagram
page for instance, right? Check this
out.
This is something I put on Instagram la
what? Yeah, 2024 is last year. This is a
coin. It's an ancient coin. It's and and
this is the coin of the Persian ruler
Vahhabar
from about 200 to 164 BC roughly. And it
depicts the king slaying a Yavana
soldier, a Greek soldier. And the
question I've asked over here is what
garment is the king wearing below the
waist? What is it called today? Is this
still still worn anywhere? And if you
look at the garment, yeah, let's bigify
this. If you look at the garment, it is
clearly a doi.
It's a Persian king wearing a doti in
battle. Isn't that interesting? Right.
So it was cool in Persia
um 2,000 years ago. So it's it's
something that we can bring back anytime
if if you want to. But we don't think it
is it is cool today. It is not cool. No.
Feminist Slayer says who was Ragnar Loth
Brock and why is this significant in
Viking history? Well, Ragnar Lbrook is
very famous today because they made a
whole series out of around his around
his life story, right? Vikings and they
also brought in Rolo into the series.
So, Ragna Ragnar is considered to be a
semi-leendary king.
Apparently, historians say that his
historicity is not entirely confirmed.
Well, I'm kind of perplexed. It is not.
So, he was a king. He was he was a
chieftain in in Scandinavia. Scandinavia
is the Nordic countries, you know,
Sweden, Denmark, all that. Mainly,
Denmark, Norway, Norway, Sweden, that
area. So, he was probably Danish or
Norwegian
somewhere around there. Yeah. Um
and
he is someone who perhaps would have
been one of the principal um principal
actors in the beginning of the Viking
age which is the beginning of the Viking
invasions of England. It would be he
probably he or one of his contemporaries
would have launched that one of the
first raids that happened on Lindes farm
where all these uh
where the monks were slaughtered and the
in in the monasteries gold and valuables
were carted back to Scandinavia. Um so
Ragnar Lbrook was a was a king. He
eventually became a king. I suppose I'm
not sure if he was born into nobility or
royalty, but he became a king and he
apparently had multiple wives and lots
of children, lots of sons and he
launched multiple invasions of England
and he was eventually captured by King
of North Umbre North Umbria
and he was executed in a very strange
manner. He was thrown into a pit that
was full of snakes. So the snakes bit
him and he died.
And so the king of North Umbrea, King
Ella, he killed Ragnar. And the word
reached Scandinavia. And Ragnar had a
whole bunch of sons. So his sons
obviously were not very pleased that
their father was killed by the by an
English king. So they brought together
an army and they invaded England. And
that is called the great heathen
invasion or the great Viking invasion
which happened in the 9th century. And
it really happened. That is not
legendary.
And the English records say that there
was an invasion by Vikings, a great
invasion of heathens, unwashed
non-Christians, pagans, polytheists. And
the uh the the Viking sagas say that
this was an invasion done by the sons of
Faragnal Loth Brock to take revenge for
for vengeance for the death death of the
father and they conquered almost all of
England apart from what Alfred King
Alfred the great whatever territory he
he commanded he was able to safeguard
that but everything else came under Dne
law the law of the Danes.
So Ragnarok was very significant and he
had multiple sons who went on to be
legendary kings in their own right like
be iron side and uh Ivar the boneless
and s what snake in the eye some some
and so on and he was known to have
multiple wives at various points in his
life right
Adita Kumar says why did the raiding of
monasteries by the Northmen, the
Vikings. Why did it not lead to the
development of a faction of warrior
monks who could defend the sad
monasteries?
Well,
in a society you have division of labor.
We are familiar with that. Do you expect
the teachers? See, for example, we know
what happened in Nalanda. The barbarian
Turks came and burned Nalanda. Why were
they able to do this? because they had
defeated the kings who protected
Nalanda.
So in a civilized society like we used
to be you had division of labor. The the
monks, the teachers, the gurus, the who
were brahmans in in the monastery,
they would not do any fighting. Why
should they do fighting? The kings would
do the fighting. The kings were the were
the defenders of the realm. They would
have armies. it was their job. So in a
in a in an advanced society, people
specialize
in a tribe,
you generalize. You should know
everything. If required, you should be
able to fight. If required, you should
be able to do something else. You should
be able to hunt and so on. But in a in a
civilized advanced civilized society,
you specialize and you stick to only
that. So even England was kind of
advanced. It was no longer tribal and it
was a Christian society and in
Christianity the monks they they they're
supposed to be cloistered in the
closters and and pray and dedicate their
their life to the service of his lord
his holiness Jesus Christ I suppose
right so monks did not fight the kings
who protected the monasteries they were
supposed to take care of the of the
protection of the monasteries so there
was a deal of course you have exceptions
of course you have exceptions we of
Bodhi Dharma who was an Indian monk who
went to China and he had to teach them
how to fight. So may so it is said that
he was actually a chhatri he was not a
brahman right he was the son of some
king in southern India apparently that's
what the Chinese say so he came from
southern India he was the son he was a
prince a prince is taught how to fight a
prince knows how to fight right and
that's why he was a he was able to teach
the the monks of Shaolin temple how to
fight and that fighting style is now
called kung fu in Christianity also you
have exceptions if you uh if you read
the the the legend of Robin Hood
which originates in the what 1200 1300s
around that time in England you had this
this monk correct prior Tuck Prior Tuck
is a character obviously this could just
be entirely legendary but legends need
to have some semblance to reality
otherwise they don't become popular so
the in the legend of Robin Hood you have
one of his one of his u
one of his followers or one of his close
associates who is called Frier Tuck who
is a who is a monk who a frier
And he's fond of drinking. He's fond of
eating a lot. And he's fond of fighting.
He's a good fighter. He's a pretty fit
man, fat man, but strong man. So you
have exceptions everywhere. But overall,
monks were not expected to fight. Monks
were expected to pray. And the king was
supposed to protect the monks and didn't
work. Some sometimes doesn't work, you
see.
Okay. Um,
Ajing Gapawar says, "What's your opinion
about the theory that states the painter
has actually escaped from Germany to
somewhere in South America along with a
few Nazi leaders?" Look, it is known
that a few Nazi leaders were indeed
present in, for example, Argentina,
right? Adolf Aikman, where was he
discovered?
Israeli the Mossad discovered Adolf
Akman in Buenosiris
and they sent a team to of Mossad agents
to Buenosiris. They abducted Adolf
Aikman, drugged him and sent him back to
Israel on a on a on a flight and he was
tried in Israel and he was executed.
That's Adolf Akman who was a very high
ranking Nazi official. The Israelis
apparently even discovered
Dr. Mangel in u Argentina but they had a
choice. They had to make a choice. It's
either either Akman or Mangel and they
suppose I think Akman was a higher
ranking guy. That's why they decided to
go with Akman. And it's not just like
you only had Adolf Akman and Mangel in
Argentina. you had many other uh former
Nazis who had escaped Europe and and
settled in Argentina. Today you will
find many Argentinian people who speak
Spanish who have got first names like
Carlo and Gustavo
but they have German last names which is
very interesting. So it's possible the
painter himself may have made the
journey across the Atlantic. It's
possible because when it comes to the
painter, have we ever found his body? Do
we have any actual evidence that he
died? The newspapers shouted the painter
is dead. But was there any evidence? It
is said that the Soviets took his body
and disposed of it or whatever. Why
would they not parade it? He was their
arch enemy.
He launched operation, what was it
called?
Barbarosa,
right? He was the great evil who bled so
many Russians who who caused so much
destruction and death to to Russia. Why
will the the Soviets not show his body?
So there's the possibility that that the
painter may actually have escaped. The
possibility exists. But do we have
proof? We don't. Okay. Proof doesn't
exist. Possibility exists. Let us take
some questions from the comments. I
still have more questions that I can go
through but it will take a long time. I
will take questions from the comments
for a while and then we shall end this.
Uh right. Okay. What? Yes. Barbar Roa.
Shar Vladimir Putin says it is Barbar
Roa. We get it. And I Why are you guys
taking super chats today? Why?
This is not a super chat session.
Okay, I will finish the super chats
quickly. See, please. This is not a
super chat question. I'm I'm sure you
did not realize it. I should have been
more clear. And the fault is mine. Let's
quickly go through super chats, but only
if it is about history. I will not take
non-history questions. What is the first
one? One second. Let me um Yeah. How
might Indian history have looked if
naval dominance had been prioritized the
way it was in Europe, the way it was
with the Cholas and the Sat Vahas?
Well, that's a completely hypothetical
question. Um
see
na we were navally dominant even during
the Marata period, right?
uh we prioritized no dominance for the
longest time.
If you look at the Harapan period,
we had gigantic docks.
The dock the port at Lothal
and the port at Dool Vira, they they
have harbors that compare favorably with
the port in Vishaka Patnam where you can
dock an aircraft carrier.
And even during the Gupta period for
example
when um Samudra Gupta conquered the
entire subcontinent
especially by conquering the southern
part of India his conquest of southern
India was a two-pronged conquest.
It was a landbased conquest and also a
conquest in parallel at sea. He had a
powerful navy. But we will not be taught
any of this in our NCERT textbooks.
That's the problem. He had a powerful
navy. The Maratas had a powerful navy.
We our our empires always prioritize the
navy. They always had powerful navies.
But we are not taught this. We had the
great Marata Admiral Shri Anoji Angre
who won so many who never lost a battle
I believe right a naval battle. So we
had that but we are not taught these
things. That's the problem.
Godliness says cast reservation work. We
talking history sir today. Please sir
please we talk history today. We'll not
take and anyway don't talk about
internal matters. I talk about history
science geopolitics. I don't talk about
cast issues today. I don't talk about
vaka board. I don't talk about these
things. Internal politics. Yeah, that's
something I am not a not I don't deal in
that. Sorry, sir. We talk about history.
Uh what is next? Uh Koshel says causes
for the fall of Roman Republic includes
one increase in inequality between the
slaveolding class and con people.
Increasing use of political violence. I
see the same thing in America. Agree.
The incre the call for the the cause for
the fall of the Roman Republic
does include all of these things. Yes.
And even the fall of the Roman Empire.
See the cause for the fall of any system
is the weakening of the system.
You may have inequality but as long as
the system is strong nothing nothing can
be done about it. When the system
becomes weak that's when the inequality
becomes weaponized.
You may have a nation where you have 1%
people who rule 99% people who are
slaves. We just take took a look at at
an example where you had 20,000 British
occupiers who ruled over 330 million
Indians.
Isn't that shocking inequality? But as
long as they have the power, they they
wield the power in the right way, they
the Indians can't do a thing.
So what you are saying is true. You are
you are seeing rising inequality in
America. No question about it. No
question. You're also seeing an increase
in political violence and the Charlie K
thing is like something all Indians are
obsessed about for some reason right
now. But whatever it's it's an indicator
of the rise in political violence. No
question. Um but as long as the American
system remains strong and the
politicians have the power in their
hands which is the armed forces the
nuclear the nuclear option and the
police force then there's nothing the
common Americans can do about it. It's
only if they lose their control over
these these tools that America could u
be on the way
the same way the Roman Roman Republic
went. Arush Mahajan thank you so much
sir. Thank you.
Arush says, "Well, thank you Arouch.
First of all, we met in Pune Hayat."
Okay. I Okay, it's good. Good then. Uh
I'm sure if I meet you again, I'll I'll
be able to remember that. So, good to
hear from you, sir. I hope you're doing
well. Abida Singh says in Shivuran
there's a story where Daksha gets his 27
daughters married to Chandra or Soma
that is a moon and he used to spend most
time with Rohini. How we know that the
elliptical course of the moon?
Uh we know the constellation where the
moon transits is exactly the same one.
It's interesting. It's interesting. You
see many of these stories
have in India in India look we our our
ancient our ancestors did not expect
everyone to understand science. Let's
say you are a ship builder. Let's say
you are a cloth merchant. Let's say you
are a metallergist who making who is
smelting steel. Let's say you're into
some other business. Everybody was in
some business, right? India was a fully
industrialized civilization. So you had
people who were in all these occupations
and they did not have the time or the
inclination to know science. So how do
you bring scientific concepts into
common understanding? by by crafting
this beautiful beautiful tales,
right? So that's how the the
astronomical
facts become woven into stories you
teach your children. So children grow up
learning these stories and then one day
when they realize it's an there's an
astronomical
uh fact that matches it they will
immediately be able to match the story
with the astronomical fact. So that's
how you can bring the scientific world
into into the common common people's
lives by creating these interesting
stories and tales and and if they these
include divinities like like the moon is
a divinity and so on then it makes it
even more powerful. So that is how we
used to have you know we used to
transmit knowledge education and so on
and today it's the it's very different.
It was so easy earlier right if if it
was done this way.
Himmanu says Rahul Gandhi will speak to
Trump. All right sir, we are discussing
history today sir. We are discussing
history today and I will not discuss
Indian politics. I stay out of Indian
politics even if it is Yeah. So okay
Mohit but says vers was the most two
three of ancient Egypt a good emperor.
How much did the Egyptian civilization
did ex um I don't remember this
particular king manos
the third I have the book right here but
it's been a long time since I read it
and there are so many kings and queens
of the Egyptian empire okay let me do a
book recommendation give me a second I
will be right back in like 10 seconds
give me a second Yeah.
And we are right back. So if you want
the answer, I don't remember right now
that was the third, but if you want the
answer, this is a great book. The rise
and the fall of ancient Egypt by Toby
Wilkinson.
And I am pretty sure that I'll be able
to find the answer in this one. It's
been a while since I read through read
through the book. So I don't remember.
See that's the deal. People ask me, let
me use this to illustrate a different
point. People ask me all the time, how
do you retain everything you read? Well,
here's an example of me not retaining
everything I read. It's impossible to
retain everything you read. You have to
give yourself permission to forget
things. You're not supposed to be a a
hard drive that stores facts and data.
You should understand causality, cause
and effect. How did things happen? But
specific facts, the the life history of
a specific king somewhere, it's okay to
forget. It's okay to forget. So, um,
Moit Mohit, I'm sorry. I don't remember
this right now. It's been a long time
since I read the read this part of
history. But here's a great book
recommendation for you, Mohit, and for
anybody else who is interested in Egypt.
This is a great book. All right, let's
let's move on. Let's go to the next
question. AKS Baga says, "Are Russian
demographics as bad as China?" No, I
don't think Russia's TFR is as Are you
talking about TFR? I hope not. Not Not
demographics.
Uh China's TFR, the last time I saw it,
total fertility rate was, I think, 1.1
or 1.2, which is horrific. And Russia's
TFR is is not that bad.
Uh, okay. Let's let's quickly see if we
can find information on Google. Um,
Russia
Russia TFR 2025.
Okay, Russia's TFR is about 1.41 or
1.42. Okay, this is a very brief I'm not
sure if it's the exact correct number,
but yeah, this is what AI is telling us.
Google's AI. I'm not doing a proper
detailed fact check here. Just a very
quick check fact check. Let's see.
China's TFR. China TFR 2025. What is it?
It's 1.02
1.02.9.
My goodness. It is worse than last time
I saw. So, as you can see, Russia's TFR
is nothing as bad as China's. China is
in is in a bad situation.
Wow. Ramachandra, thank you, sir. No
question. But all right. Thank you so
much. Uh Dig Vijay says, "I am more left
liberals often differ. That's fine. But
your views push me to think deeper. We
grow by learning across perspectives. I
even use ask this is my gym podcast."
Well, thank you so much, sir. I am
really honored. It's okay to be whatever
you are. Look, whatever we believe,
whatever worldview we have, it is
it is caused by the kind of life we have
had, the kind of upbringing we had, the
kind of teachers we had, the kind of
textbooks we had, the kind of parents we
had, the kind of family we were born in,
the kind of friends we had, all of this
comes together that it in in it
influences the way we see the world. So,
it's okay to be whoever you are. It's
not like we I will only speak It's not
like we should only speak to people who
have exactly the same thoughts and same
beliefs as us. We should talk to
everyone and it is perfectly fine to
have different opinions. You know, I'll
tell you something. In the 2000s, I used
to consider myself to be liberal.
Why did I consider myself to be liberal?
Because I enjoyed meeting people of
different backgrounds.
There are some people who only want to
be
who only want to have friends who speak
the same language and have the same
exact same food choices. Everything
everything should be the same. I only
want people who are exactly like me. Me,
I'm the exact opposite. I enjoy having
friends who are from very diverse
backgrounds, different countries,
different cultures, different
backgrounds, different whatever,
different languages, even different
religions. I don't care. It it it gives
you it makes the world more interesting
if you if you have friends like that. I
always enjoyed having friends from
different parts of the world and that's
why I considered myself to be liberal
because I had a very open mind. I still
have a very open mind. Then later on I
unders I got to know that the the term
liberal has been captured by the left.
That whatever the left is that is
liberal and everyone else is
right-winger. From that perspective then
I would be a right-winger because I'm
not that I'm not a Marxist. I'm not a
leftist. I'm not a socialist. I'm not a
communist. So that automatically makes
me right. So the truth is I am liberal.
I respect everyone as long as they
respect me. I enjoy very diverse
company.
But I am not a lefty.
Okay. But but that's okay. That's okay.
So my my point is look, it's okay to
have different opinions. It doesn't mean
that we have to be enemies or we have to
fight. We can be friends. I as long as
you know I'll be happy to be friends
with anybody as long as they're not
anti- my civilization in my country.
That's it. You can be of whatever
religion. You can speak whatever
language. You can even eat whatever food
you want. I don't care. As long as you
are not actively harming my culture, my
civilization and my country, I'm
perfectly fine. But that's all. Right.
Okay. Next. D Vijay says to be clear,
I'm not saying I change my views. I
respect the intellect helping me helps
me avoid echo chambers and test my own
own ideas. Perfectly fine. I'm not
asking you to change your views. Just
have an open mind and and and and
at least hear everyone out. It's you
should you should be exposed to all
kinds of ideas and then you can choose
whether you want to agree or disagree
with them. That's entirely your choice.
And it's glad that you have this I'm
glad to see that you have this open
mind. So good to see that, sir. Good to
see that. All right. Galler says Trump's
breaking a Okay, this is sir this is
geopolitics. We're discussing
geopolitics tomorrow sir please. Today
we only discuss history otherwise it's
no longer a history liveream and I'm I'm
letting my audience down who who have
all come to watch geopolitics I mean
sorry history right please sir let us
stick to history today.
Um
Rahul says not a question but a
suggestion. There are some trolls who
frequent the live chat and dirty the
discussion. Having moderators will help.
I have at least one moderator. Well, I
will remind the moderator to do a good
to do a better job. But anyway, thank
you for pointing this out. I I
appreciate that and it is noted. Your
point is noted. And the last question
for today is by Galler. Why was the mass
why was the massacre Pquart misnomered
in Mobyick? Anglo-Saxon arrogance or
innocent for folly like M fobedic.
Moby Dick is a fascinating story. What's
the first sentence
in the book the one of the most epic
opening lines? Call me Ishmael and
that's the narrative. Now the problem is
that I read Moby Dick and I was
fascinated with the story with with the
whole time period and that that mill but
the last time I read Moby Dick was when
I was like a 15 years old.
That's been a long time. I don't
remember the story today. I remember it
was fascinating. It was all alled with
veiling. You have Captain Ahab. You have
uh Quiqu
and and so on. But I don't remember the
story. Um I remember the white whale.
Captain Ahab was obsessed with the white
whale.
Um so I I don't remember right now. Once
again, you see, I don't retain
everything. It's been so long. So long.
So yeah, I'm sorry I won't be able to
answer this because I don't remember the
story anymore. I and reading that book
again, it's it's a huge time investment.
That's a big book. And I remember it's
not an easy read. It's a fascinating
read, but not an easy read and it would
take me some time to read it today. So
I'm sure I'll not have the time right
now to read it. So right now I can't
answer your question. But anyway, thank
you so much for asking the question and
uh yeah. Okay, folks. That's that's it.
That's it. I'm going to have to end this
now. This is a regular live stream. It's
not not one of those 8 hour live streams
that I can't do every every weekend.
So, um, so let's end this now and I
shall see you tomorrow 8:00 p.m. India
time and tomorrow we shall talk about
geopolitics
and
I'll take all the questions as many as
possible mainly from the super chat but
everything is welcome. All right people,
thank you so much.
And good night, good day to everybody,
all my friends. Guitar when you know
what, it's been a long time since I
played the guitar in any seriousness. I
have three guitars hanging there. They
need new strings. They still have the
strings and I have my amp over here, the
electric guitar amplifier. It's been a
long time. If I play right now, I will
sound terrible. So, maybe I should
practice for a while before I play the
guitar. Yeah, I used to be a good
musician. I I am I am a lapsed musician.
I used to be a really good guitarist.
Anyway, maybe sometime in the future
I'll I'll bring out my guitar and do the
intro with the guitar. All right,
people. I'll see you tomorrow. Thank
you. Bye-bye. Take care and keep raising
your standards. Never forget that.
Bye-bye.